The clouds burst.
Next day the trumpets rang early in the camp. Soon a single runner was seen
hurrying along the narrow path. At a distance he stood and held them, asking
whether Thoren would now listen to another embassy since new tidings had
come to hand and matters were changed.
"That will be Dne," said Thoren when he heard. "They will have got wind of his
coming. I thought that would alter their mood. Bid them come few in number and
weaponless, and I will hear, he called to the messenger. About midday the
banners of the forest and the lake were seen to be born forth again. A company
of 20 was approaching. At the beginning of the narrow way, they laid aside sword
and spear and came on towards the gate.
wondering, the dwarves saw that among them were both Bard and the Elden King,
before whom an old man wrapped in cloak and hood bore a strong casket of
ironbound wood. Hail Thorin, said Bard, are you still of the same mind? My mind
does not change with the rising and setting of a few sons, answered Thoren.
Did you come to ask me idle questions?
Still the elf host has not departed as I bade. Till then you come in vain to
bargain with me. Is there then nothing for which you would yield any of your
gold? Nothing that you or your friends have to offer. What of the arkham stone
of drain? said he, and at the same moment the old man opened the casket and
held aloft the jewel. The light leapt from his hand, bright and white in the
morning. Then Thoren was stricken dumb with amazement and confusion. No one
spoke for a long while.
Thoren at length broke the silence, and his voice was thick with wrath. "That
stone was my father's and is mine," he said. "Why should I purchase my own?"
But wonder overcame him, and he added, "But how came you by the heirloom of my
house, if there is need to ask such a question of thieves?" "We are not
thieves," Bart answered. "Your own we will give back in return for our own."
How can you buy it?" shouted Thoren in gathering rage. "I gave it to them,"
squeaked Bilbo, who was peering over the wall by now in a dreadful fright. "You,
you!" cried Thoren, turning upon him and grasping him with both hands. "You
miserable hobbit! You undersize burglar!" he shouted at a loss for
words, and he shook poor Bilbo like a rabbit. by the beard of Duran. I wish I
had Gandalf here. Curse him for his choice of you. May his beard wither. As
for you, I will throw you to the rocks.
He cried and lifted Bilbo in his arms.
"Stay! Your wish is granted," said a voice. The old man with the casket to
recside his hood and cloak. "Here is Gandalf, and none too soon, it seems. If
you don't like my burglar, please don't damage him. Put him down and listen
first to what he has to say. You all seem in league, said Thoren, dropping
Bilbo on the top of the wall. Never again will I have dealings with any
wizard or his friends. What of you to say, you descendant of rats?
Dear me, dear me, said Bilbo. I am sure this is all very uncomfortable. You may
remember saying that I might choose my own 14th share. Perhaps I took it too
literally. I have been told that dwarves are sometimes politer in word than
indeed. The time was all the same when you seemed to think that I had been of
some service. Descendant of rats indeed.
Is this all the service of you and your family that I was promised Thoren? Take
it that I have disposed of my share as I
wished and let it go at that. I will," said Thorin grimly, "and I will let you
go at that, and may we never meet again." Then he turned and spoke over
the wall. "I am betrayed," he said. "It was rightly guessed that I could not
forebeare to redeem the Arkanstone, the treasure of my house. For it I will give
1/14th share of the horde in silver and gold, setting aside the gems. But that
shall be account of the promise share of this traitor. And with that reward he
shall depart, and you can divide it as you will. He will get little enough. I
doubt not. Take him if you wish him to live, and no friendship of mine goes
with him. Get down now to your friends, he said to Bilbo, "Or I will throw you
down." "What about the gold and silver?"
asked Bilbo. That shall follow after as can be arranged, said he. Get down.
Until then, we keep the stone, cried Bard. You are not making a very splendid
figure as king under the mountain, said Gandalf. But things may change yet. They
may indeed," said Thorin. And already so strong was the bewilderment of the
treasure upon him, he was pondering whether by the help of Dne might not
recapture the arkan stone, and withhold the share of the reward. And so Bilbo
was swung down from the wall, and departed with nothing for all his
trouble, except the armor which Thoren had given him already. More than one of
the dwarves in their hearts felt shame and pity at his going. Farewell, he
cried to them. We may meet again as friends.
Be off, cold Thorin. You have mail upon you, which was made by my folk, and is
too good for you. It cannot be pierced by arrows. But if you do not hasten, I
will sting your miserable feet. So be swift.
Not so hasty, said Bard. We will give you until tomorrow. At noon we will
return and see if you have brought from the horde the portion that is to be set
against the stone. If that is done without deceit, then we will depart, and
the elf host will go back to the forest.
In the meanwhile, farewell.
With that they went back to the camp.
But Thoren sent messengers by Roy, telling Dne of what had passed, and
bidding him come with wary speed. That day passed in the night. The next day
the wind shifted west and the air was dark and gloomy. The morning was still
early when a cry was heard in the camp.
Runners came in to report that a host of dwarves had appeared round the eastern
spur of the mountain and was now hastening to Dale. Dne had come. He had
hurried on through the night and so had come upon them sooner than they had
expected. Each one of his folk was clad in a harbor of steel male that hung to
his knees, and his legs were covered with hose of a fine and flexible metal
mesh, the secret of whose making was possessed by Dne's people. The dwarves
are exceedingly strong for their height, but most of these were strong, even for
dwarves. In battle, they wielded heavy two-handed Mattoxs, but each of them had
also a short, broad sword at his side and a round shield slung at his back.
Their beards were forked and plated and thrust into their belts. Their caps were
of iron, and they were shot with iron, and their faces were grim. Trumpets
called men and elves to arms. Before long, the dwarves could be seen coming
up the valley at a great pace. They halted between the river and the eastern
spur, but a few held on their way, and crossing the river drew near the camp,
and there they laid down their weapons and held up their hands in sign of
peace. Bard went out to meet them and with him went Bilbo. We are sent from
Dne son of Naine, they said when questioned. We are hastening to our
kinsmen in the mountain since we learned that the kingdom of old is renewed.
But who are you that sit in the plain as foes before defended walls? This, of
course, in the polite and rather old-fashioned language of such
occasions, meant simply, "You have no business here. We are going on, so make
way, or we shall fight you." They meant to push on between the mountain and the
loop of the river, for the narrow land there did not seem to be strongly
guarded. Bard, of course, refused to allow the dwarfs to go straight on to
the mountain. He was determined to wait until the gold and silver had been
brought out in exchange for the Arkanstone, for he did not believe that
this would be done if once the fortress was manned with so large and warlike a
company. They had brought with them a great store of supplies, for the dwarves
can carry very heavy burdens, and nearly all of Dne's folk, in spite of their
rapid march, bore huge packs on their backs in addition to their weapons. They
would stand a siege for weeks, and by that time yet more dwarves might come,
and yet more, for Thoren had many relatives. Also, they would be able to
reopen and guide some other gate, so that the besieggers would have to
encircle the whole mountain, and for that they had not sufficient numbers.
These were, in fact, precisely their plans, for the raven messengers had been
busy between Thoren and Dne, but for the moment the way was barred. So after
angry words, the dwarf messengers retired, muttering in their beards. Bard
then sent messengers at once to the gate, but they found no gold or payment.
Arrows came forth as soon as they were within shot, and they hastened back in
dismay. In the camp all was now a st as if for battle, for the dwarves of Dne
were advancing along the eastern bank.
Fools, laughed Bard, to come thus beneath the mountains arm. They do not
understand war above ground, whatever they may know of battle in the mines.
There are many of our archers and spearmen now hidden in the rocks upon
their right flank. Dwarf Male may be good, but they will soon be hardput to
it. Let us set on them now from both sides before they are fully rested.
But the oven king said, "Long will I tar I begin this war for gold." The dwarves
cannot pass us unless we will or do anything that we cannot mark. Let us
hope still for something that will bring reconciliation.
Our advantage in numbers will be enough if in the end it must come to unhappy
blows. But he reckoned without the dwarves. The knowledge that the
Arkanstone was in the hands of the besieures burned in their thoughts. Also
they guessed the hesitation of Bard and his friends and resolved to strike while
they debated. Suddenly, without a signal, they sprang silently forward to
attack. Bows twanged and arrows whistled. Battle was about to be joined.
Still more suddenly a darkness came on with dreadful swiftness. A black cloud
hurried over the sky. Winter thunder on a wild wind rolled roaring up and
rumbled in the mountain, and lightning lit its peak. And beneath the thunder,
another blackness could be seen whirling forward, but it did not come with the
wind. It came from the north like a vast cloud of birds, so dense that no light
could be seen between their wings.
"Halt!" cried Gandalf, who appeared suddenly, and stood alone with arms
uplifted between the advancing dwarves and the ranks awaiting them. "Halt!" He
called in a voice like thunder, and his staff blazed forth with a flash like the
lightning. Dread has come upon you all.
Alas, it is come [clears throat] more swiftly than I guest. The goblins are
upon you. Bold of the north is coming, O Dne, whose father you slew in Moria.
Behold, the bats are above his army like a sea of locusts. They ride upon wolves,
and wars are in their train. Amazement and confusion fell upon them all. Even
as Gandalf had been speaking, the darkness grew. The dwarves halted and
gazed at the sky. The elves cried out with many voices. "Come," called
Gandalf. "There is yet time for counsel.
Let Dne, son of Naine, come swiftly to us." So began a battle that none had
expected, and it was called the battle of five armies, and it was very
terrible. Upon one side were the goblins and the wild wolves, and upon the other
were elves and men and dwarves. This is how it fell out. Ever since the fall of
the great goblin of the Misty Mountains, the hatred of their race for the dwarves
had been rekindled to fury. Messengers had passed to and fro between all their
cities, colonies, and strongholds. For they resolved now to win the dominion of
the north tidings they had gathered in secret ways. And in all the mountains
there was a forging and an arming. Then they marched and gathered by hill and
valley, going ever by tunnel or under dark until around and beneath the great
mountain Gundabbad of the north where was their capital. A vast host was
assembled ready to sweep down in time of storm unawares upon the south. Then they learned of the
death of smog, and joy was in their hearts. And they hastened night after
night through the mountains, and came thus at last on a sudden from the north
hard on the hills of Dne. Not even the ravens knew of their coming until they
came out in the broken lands which divided the lonely mountain from the
hills behind. How much Gandalf knew cannot be said, but it is plain that he
had not expected this sudden assault.
This is the plan that he made in council with the elven king and with Bard and
with Dne for the dwarf lord now joined them. The goblins were the foes of all
and at their coming all other quarrels were forgotten. Their only hope was to
lure the goblins into the valley between the arms of the mountain and themselves
to man the great spurs that struck south and east. Yet this would be perilous if
the goblins were in sufficient numbers to overrun the mountain itself, and so
attack them also from behind and above.
But there was no time to make any other plan or to summon any help. Soon the
thunder passed, rolling away to the southeast, but the backcloud came,
flying lower over the shoulder of the mountain, and whirled above them,
shutting out the light and filling them with dread. To the mountain, called
Borrowed. To the mountain, let us take our places while there is yet time. On
the southern spur, in its lower slopes, and in the rocks at its feet, the elves
were set. On the eastern spur were men and dwarves, but Bard and some of the
nimblest of men and elves climbed to the height of the eastern shoulder to gain a
view to the north. Soon they could see the lands before the mountains feet
black with a hurrying multitude. Air long the vanguard swirled round the
spurs end and came rushing into Dale.
These were the swiftest wolf riders and already their cries and howls rent the
air a few brave men were strong before them to make a fate of resistance and
many there fell before the rest drew back and fled to either side. As Gandalf
had hoped, the goblin army had gathered behind the resisted vanguard and poured
now in rage into the valley, driving wildly up between the arms of the
mountain, seeking for the foe. Their banners were countless, black and red,
and they came on like a tide in fury and disorder.
It was a terrible battle, the most dreadful of all Bilbo's experiences, and
the one which at the time he hated most,
which is to say it was the one he was most proud of, and most fond of
recalling long afterwards, although he was quite unimportant in it. Actually, I
may say he put on his ring early in the business, and vanished from sight, if
not from all danger. A magic ring of that sort is not a complete protection
in a goblin charge, nor does it stop flying arrows and wild spears, but it
does help in getting out of the way, and it prevents your head from being
specially chosen for a sweeping stroke by a goblin swordsman. The elves were
the first to charge. Their hatred for the goblins is cold and bitter, their
spears and swords shone in the gloom with a gleam of chill flame. So deadly
was the wrath of the hands that held them. As soon as the host of their
enemies was dense in the valley, they sent against it a shower of arrows, and
each flickered as it fled as if with stinging fire. Behind the arrows, a
thousand of their spearmen leapt down and charged. The yells were deafening,
the rocks were stained black with goblin blood. Just as the goblins were
recovering from the onslaught and the elf charge was halted, there rose from
across the valley a deep throatated roar. With cries of Moria and Dane, Dne
Dne the dwarves of the iron hills plunged in, wielding their mattoox upon
the other side, and beside them came the men of the lake with long swords.
Panic came upon the goblins, and even as they turned to meet this new attack, the
elves charged again with renewed numbers. Already many of the goblins
were flying back down the river to escape from the trap, and many of their
own wolves were turning upon them and rending the dead and the wounded.
Victory seemed at hand when a cry rang out on the heights above.
Goblins had scaled the mountain from the other side, and already many were on the
slopes above the gate, and others were streaming down recklessly, heaveless of
those that fell screaming from cliff and precipice to attack the spurs from
above. Each of these could be reached by paths that ran down from the main mass
of the mountain in the center, and the defenders had too few to bar the way for
long. Victory now vanished from hope.
They had only stemmed the first onslaught of the black tide. Day drew
on. The goblins gathered again in the valley. There a host of wards came
ravening and with them came the bodyguard of bold. Goblins of huge size
with scimitars of steel. Soon actual darkness was coming into a stormy sky.
While still the great bats swirled about the heads and ears of elves and men wore
fastened vampire light on the stricken.
Now Bard was fighting to defend the eastern spur, and yet giving slowly
back, and the elf lords were at bay about their king upon the southern arm,
near to the watchpost on Raven Hill.
Suddenly there was a great shout, and from the gate came a tropic call. They
had forgotten Thorin. Part of the wall, moved by levers, fell outward with a
crash into the pool. Out leapt the king under the mountain, and his companions
followed him. Hood and Cloak were gone.
They were in shining armor, and red light leapt from their eyes. In the
gloom, the great dwarf gleamed like gold in a dying fire. Rocks were hurled down
from on high by the goblins above, but they held on, leapt down to the fall's
foot, and rushed forward to battle. Wolf and Ryder fell or fled before them.
Thoren wielded his ax with mighty strokes, and nothing seemed to harm him.
To me, to me, elves and men, to me, oh my kinsfolk, he cried, and his voice
shook like a horn in the valley. Down heless of order, rushed all the dwarves
of Dne to his help. Down too came many of the lakemen, for Bard could not
restrain them, and out upon the other side came many of the spearmen of the
elves. Once again the goblins were stricken in the valley and they were
piled in heaps till Dale was dark and hideous with their corpses. The wards
were scattered and Thorin drove right against the bodyguard of Bulg. But he
could not pierce their ranks.
Already behind him among the goblin dead lay many men and many dwarves and many a
fair elf that should have lived yet long ages merrily in the wood. And as the
valley widened his onset grew ever slower. His numbers were too few. His
flanks were unguarded. Soon the attackers were attacked, and they were
forced into a great ring, facing every way, hemmed all about, with goblins and
wolves, returning to the assault. The bodyguard of Bold came howling against
them, and drove in upon their ranks like waves upon cliffs of sand. Their friends
could not help them, for the assault from the mountain was renewed with
redoubled force, and upon either side men and elves were being slowly beaten
down. On all this Bilbo looked with misery. He had taken his stand on Ravenh
Hill among the elves, partly because there was more chance of escape from
that point, and partly with the more Turkish part of his mind, because if he
was going to be in a last desperate stand, he preferred on the whole to
defend the elven king. Gandalf, too, I may say, was there sitting on the ground
as if in deep thought, preparing, I suppose, some last blast of magic before
the end. That did not seem far off. It will not be long now, thought Bilbo,
before the goblins win the gate, and we are all slaughtered or driven down and captured.
Really, it is enough to make one weep.
After all, one has gone through. I would rather old smog had been left with all
the wretched treasure than that these vile creatures should get it and poor
old Bomber and Balin and Philly and Killy and all the rest come to a bad end
and Bard too and the lakemen and the merry elves misery me. I have heard
songs of many battles and I have always understood that defeat may be glorious.
It seems very uncomfortable not to say distressing. I wish I was well out of
it. The clouds were torn by the wind, and a red sunset slashed the west.
Seeing the sudden gleam in the gloom, Bilbo looked round. He gave a great cry.
He had seen a sight that made his heart leap. Dark shapes small yet majestic
against the distant glow. "The eagles!
The eagles!" he shouted. "The eagles are coming!" Bilbo's eyes were seldom wrong.
The eagles were coming down the wind, line after line, in such a host as must
have gathered from all the iies of the north. The eagles, the eagles, Bilbo
cried, dancing and waving his arms. If the elves could not see him, they could
hear him. Soon they too took up the cry, and it echoed across the valley. Many
wandering eyes looked up, though as yet nothing could be seen except from the
southern shoulders of the mountain.
The eagles, cried Bilbo once more, but at that moment a stone hurdling from
above smokeed heavily on his helm, and he fell with a crash and knew no more.